You would prefer the human race to endure,
여러분은 인류가 존속하기를 원하시죠,
right? You're hesitating. Yes? I don't know. I
그렇죠? 망설이시네요. 네? 모르겠습니다.
would’ This is Peter Thiel. This is a
그럴 것 같습니다. 이 사람이 피터 틸입니다. 이건
long hesitation. There's so many questions. Should the
긴 망설임이네요. 질문이 너무 많습니다. 인류가
human race survive? Yes. He's been a major
생존해야 하는가? 네. 그는 실리콘밸리에서
player in Silicon Valley for a long, long
아주 오랫동안 핵심 인물이었습니다.
time. I'm Peter Thiel. I build companies and
저는 피터 틸입니다. 저는 회사를 세우고
I support people who are building
새로운 것을 만드는 사람들을 지원합니다,
new things from social networks to rocket ships.
소셜 네트워크부터 로켓까지요.
You might know him as the multi-billionaire
여러분은 그를 억만장자로 알고 계실 겁니다.
who
그는
co-founded PayPal and Palantir. As Facebook's first
PayPal과 Palantir를 공동 창업했습니다. Facebook의 첫
outside investor. The guy who funds out their
외부 투자자로서도요. 그는 독특한 프로젝트에 자금을 지원합니다,
projects
예를 들어
like floating countries, private space travel and the
바다 위 떠다니는 국가, 민간 우주 여행,
quest for immortality. Peter Thiel rejects the idea
불멸의 추구 같은 것들입니다. 피터 틸은
that death is inevitable. He wants to transform
죽음이 피할 수 없다는 생각을 거부합니다. 그는 인류를
humanity. Transhumanism was this radical transformation
변형시키고 싶어합니다. 트랜스휴머니즘은 급진적인 변환입니다,
where your human natural body where your human
인간의 자연적인 육체가, 인간의 자연적인
natural body gets transformed into an immortal body.
육체가 불멸의 몸으로 변환되는 것입니다.
We want you to be able to change
우리는 여러분이 심장을 바꾸고
your heart and change your mind and change
마음을 바꾸고 온몸을
your whole body.
바꿀 수 있기를 원합니다.
But he also wants to change something else.
하지만 그는 다른 것도 바꾸고 싶어합니다.
For decades, Thiel has schemed from the shadows
수십 년간, 틸은 그림자 속에서
to reshape American politics.
미국 정치를 재편하려는 계획을 세워왔습니다.
Tonight, I urge all of my fellow Americans
오늘 밤, 저는 모든 미국인 동포들에게
to stand up and vote for Donald Trump.
도널드 트럼프에게 투표해 달라고 촉구합니다.
He bankrolled Trump's first campaign. He turbocharged J
그는 트럼프의 첫 번째 선거 캠페인에 자금을 댔습니다. 그는 J.D.
.D. Vance's career. Thiel openly questions the
밴스의 경력을 급성장시켰습니다. 틸은 공개적으로
democratic system. And he's declared that to him,
민주주의 체제에 의문을 제기합니다. 그는 자신에게
freedom is incompatible with democracy.
자유는 민주주의와 양립할 수 없다고 선언했습니다.
His vision of an ideal society sounds more
이상적인 사회에 대한 그의 비전은 과두제에
like an oligarchy. A country ruled by a
가깝게 들립니다. 소수의 강력하고 부유한
few powerful rich
사람들이 지배하는 나라,
people. Or even just one. Today, his influence
아니면 심지어 한 사람만으로요. 오늘날 그의 영향력은
is rapidly expanding across the world. From the
전 세계에서 빠르게 확장되고 있습니다. 그의 경력
beginning of
초기부터
his career, he's been building tools to rewire
그는 권력이 작동하는 방식을 재편하는 도구를
how power works. Palantir, his brainchild, enables intelligence
만들어왔습니다. 그의 발명품인 Palantir는 정보기관과
agencies and militaries to anticipate their enemy's next
군대가 적의 다음 움직임을 예측할 수 있게 합니다,
move before it's made. Maybe even your next
실행되기 전에요. 어쩌면 여러분의 다음 움직임도
move, too.
마찬가지일 수 있습니다.
None of this happened by accident. Peter Thiel
이 모든 것은 우연히 일어난 게 아닙니다. 피터 틸은
plays the long game. He's patiently planned his
장기전을 합니다. 그는 수십 년 동안
moves for
인내심 있게 자신의
decades, always several steps ahead. So what does
움직임을 계획해왔고, 항상 몇 수 앞서 있습니다. 그렇다면
Peter Thiel actually want?
피터 틸은 실제로 무엇을 원할까요?
What's his problem with democracy? And is there
그의 민주주의에 대한 문제는 무엇일까요? 그리고
an endgame?
최종 목표가 있을까요?
This video is largely based on the research
이 영상은 주로 『더 컨트래리언: 피터 틸과
collected in The Contrarian, Peter Thiel and
실리콘밸리의 권력 추구』에서
Silicon Valley's Pursuit of Power by Max Chavkin.
맥스 차프킨이 수집한 연구를 바탕으로 합니다.
You'll find a link in the description.
설명란에 링크가 있습니다.
New York City, 2010. A TV show has
뉴욕시, 2010년. TV 프로그램이 피터 틸이
set up a night for Peter Thiel to
게리 카스파로프를 만나는
meet Gary Kasparov,
밤을 마련했습니다.
one of the greatest chess players of all
역대 최고의 체스 선수 중
time. Thiel and Kasparov have met before and
한 명입니다. 틸과 카스파로프는 전에도 만났고
get along well.
사이가 좋습니다.
They like chatting about politics, technology, and of
그들은 정치, 기술, 그리고 물론
course, chess. Peter Thiel's a diehard chess fan.
체스에 대해 이야기하길 좋아합니다. 피터 틸은 열렬한 체스 팬입니다.
In fact, he's a national chess master. He's
사실, 그는 전국 체스 마스터입니다. 그는 십대 때부터
admired the grandmaster Kasparov since he was a
그랜드마스터 카스파로프를 존경해왔습니다.
teenager.
존경은
And the respect is mutual. Kasparov admires Thiel's
상호적입니다. 카스파로프는 틸의 지성과 비즈니스 감각을
intelligence and business sense.
존경합니다.
He is one of the probably most successful
그는 아마도 그의 세대에서 가장
entrepreneurs of his generation. He is very
성공한 기업가 중 한 명입니다. 그는 매우
aggressively investing. He looks for the future. Thiel's
공격적으로 투자합니다. 그는 미래를 봅니다. 틸의
legendary status in business is hard to
비즈니스계에서의 전설적인 지위는
overstate. His companies have created technologies that have
아무리 강조해도 지나치지 않습니다. 그의 회사들은 현대 세계의
changed the course of the modern world.
흐름을 바꾼 기술을 만들어냈습니다.
And his influence helped define tech, an industry
그의 영향력은 수백만 개의 일자리와 수조 달러의
that has produced millions of jobs and trillions
부를 창출한 산업인 기술 산업을 정의하는 데
of dollars of wealth. That night, Kasparov and
도움이 되었습니다. 그날 밤, 카스파로프와 틸은 체스 클럽을
Thiel hit up a chess club. Thiel plays
찾았습니다. 틸은 클럽 주인과
a game of
스피드 체스 한
speed chess with the owner and wins. I'm
판을 두고 이겼습니다. 저는 정말
totally embarrassed.
부끄럽습니다.
Embarrassed as well. Kasparov suggests his chess skills
저도 마찬가지로 부끄럽습니다. 카스파로프는 그의 체스 실력이
are probably why Thiel's such a successful
틸이 그토록 성공적인 사업가인 이유이고,
businessman and why he tends to hire chess
그가 자신의 회사에 체스 선수들을 고용하는
players for his companies. That's why he's hiring
이유라고 제안합니다. 그래서 그가 체스 선수들을
chess
고용하는 겁니다,
players, you know. Peter just told me the
아시죠. 피터가 방금 저에게 PayPal
story that one day he's the IPO for
IPO 날 이야기를 해줬습니다. 그는
Paypal. So he did a
PayPal 직원 10명과
simul for ten employees of Paypal. And sure,
동시 대국을 했습니다. 그리고 확실히
Thiel is probably onto something. Chess skills transfer
틸은 아마 무언가를 알고 있을 겁니다. 체스 실력은
well into the world of business. It's a
비즈니스 세계로 잘 전이됩니다. 체스는
game of strategy, where it pays off to
전략 게임이고, 몇 수 앞을
think several moves
생각하면 이득입니다.
ahead. Skills that don't hurt in politics either.
정치에서도 해롭지 않은 기술입니다.
Sometime after this evening, Kasparov and Thiel drift
그날 저녁 이후 언젠가, 카스파로프와 틸은 멀어집니다.
apart.
사이가 벌어집니다.
Maybe the two don't have that much in
어쩌면 두 사람은 그렇게까지 공통점이
common after all. It's not just that the
결국 별로 없을지도 모릅니다. 단지
Russian Kasparov is a
러시아의 카스파로프가
way better chess player. He's also one of
훨씬 더 뛰어난 체스 선수라는 것만이 아니라,
the world's most prominent pro-democracy activists.
세계에서 가장 저명한 민주주의 옹호 활동가 중 한 명이기도 합니다.
He's a major thorn in Putin's sight, tirelessly
그는 푸틴에게 큰 가시 같은 존재로, 끊임없이
campaigning for a freer Russia.
더 자유로운 러시아를 위해 캠페인을 벌이고 있습니다.
So I'm fighting to restore democracy in my
그래서 저는 제
country.
나라에서 민주주의를 되찾기 위해 싸우고 있습니다.
Trump's potential victory could threaten not only democracy
트럼프가 승리할 가능성은 이 나라의 민주주의뿐 아니라
in this country, but you know,
아시다시피,
democracy worldwide. And Peter Thiel? Well, kind of
전 세계의 민주주의를 위협할 수 있습니다. 그리고 피터 틸은요? 음, 일종의
the opposite trajectory.
정반대의 궤적을 걷고 있습니다.
Critics warn he's emerging as a major threat
비평가들은 그가 중대한 위협으로 떠오르고 있다고 경고합니다,
to American democracy.
미국 민주주의에 대한 위협으로 말입니다.
Billionaires like Thiel reshaping politics is terrifying. Connecting
틸 같은 억만장자들이 정치를 재편하는 것은 정말 무섭습니다. 하지만
to airport Wi-Fi ranks way
공항 와이파이에 접속하는 일은 훨씬
lower on the scale. But having your data
덜 심각한 문제입니다. 그렇지만 여러분의 데이터가
floating around unprotected online is a threat you
보호받지 않은 채 온라인에 떠돌아다니는 것은 여러분이
can actually
실제로
do something about. This is where today's sponsor
대처할 수 있는 위협입니다. 여기서 오늘의 스폰서가
NordVPN comes in. NordVPN encrypts your internet
NordVPN이 등장합니다. NordVPN은 여러분의 인터넷을 암호화합니다
traffic so your personal data stays private. With
트래픽을 암호화하여 개인 데이터를 안전하게 보호합니다.
the shopping season in full swing, think twice
쇼핑 시즌이 한창인 지금, 너무 좋아 보이는
before clicking that deal that looks too good
딜을 클릭하기 전에 두 번 생각하세요.
to be true. It can happen to anyone.
누구에게나 일어날 수 있는 일입니다.
Regular VPNs don't
일반 VPN은 항상
always protect you against fake web stores. NordVPN's
가짜 웹 스토어로부터 보호해주지 않습니다. NordVPN의
Threat Protection Pro helps you avoid malware,
Threat Protection Pro는 악성코드, 해커,
hackers and trackers, even when you're not connected
트래커를 피할 수 있게 해줍니다, VPN에
to a VPN. It's a certified anti-phishing
연결되어 있지 않을 때도요. 이것은 공인된
tool
피싱 방지
recognized by leading cybersecurity labs. Try NordVPN risk
도구이며, 주요 사이버보안 연구소에서 인정받았습니다. NordVPN을
-free with a 30-day money-back guarantee
30일 환불 보장과 함께 무위험으로
and
사용해보세요.
go to nordvpn.com slash ferntv for a
nordvpn.com/ferntv에서 대폭 할인과
huge discount plus 4 extra months. You can
추가 4개월을 받으세요. 또한
also scan this QR code
이 QR 코드를 스캔하거나
or check the link in the description. Wait,
설명란의 링크를 확인하세요. 잠깐,
did you actually just scan that QR code?
방금 정말로 QR 코드를 스캔하셨나요?
Peter Thiel is around 8 years old when
피터 틸은 8살 무렵 가족과 함께
his family arrives in Swakopmund, a former German
스바코프문트에 도착합니다. 나미비아 해안의
colony on
옛 독일 식민지입니다.
Namibia's coast. He moved here with his parents
그는 오하이오에서 몇 년을 보낸 후 부모님과
and brother after some years in Ohio. During
형과 함께 이곳으로 이사했습니다. 1970년대에
the 1970s,
이 도시는
the city is occupied by apartheid South Africa.
아파르트헤이트 남아프리카에 의해 점령되어 있었습니다.
At the time, it's a town clinging to
당시 이곳은 독일 뿌리에 집착하는 도시였는데,
its German roots,
독일 뿌리에 집착해
where Hitler's birthday is still celebrated and the
히틀러의 생일이 여전히 축하되고
Nazi salute is a casual greeting for some.
나치식 경례가 일부에게는 일상적인 인사였습니다.
Peter's father, Klaus, takes an engineering job at
피터의 아버지 클라우스는 도시 외곽의
a uranium mine just outside town. The mine
우라늄 광산에서 엔지니어 직책을 맡습니다. 그 광산은
is
논란이 많고
controversial and shrouded in secrecy. According to international
비밀에 싸여 있습니다. 국제법에 따르면, 남아프리카는
law, South Africa isn't allowed to
이곳에서 채굴할 수 없지만
mine here, but they go ahead anyway. Extracting
그들은 어쨌든 진행합니다. 나미비아의 우라늄 채굴은
Namibia's uranium is part of South Africa's
남아프리카 핵무기 프로그램의 일부입니다.
nuclear weapons program. The regime is secretly developing
이 정권은 소련의 공격 가능성에 대비하고
bombs to defend against a possible
아파르트헤이트 체제를 보호하기 위해
Soviet attack and to protect the apartheid way
비밀리에 핵폭탄을 개발하고 있었습니다.
of life. According to a former British activist
전 영국 활동가 단체에 따르면
group,
흑인 노동자들은
black laborers have worked at the mine under
위험한 조건에서
dangerous conditions. Meanwhile, white families
광산에서 일했습니다. 한편 틸 가족 같은
like the Thiels enjoy a privileged life. Brand
백인 가정은 특권적인 삶을 누렸습니다. 새로운
new medical facilities, country club memberships,
의료 시설, 컨트리 클럽 회원권,
kids in private school. Young Peter is reportedly
사립학교에 다니는 자녀들. 어린 피터는 처음에
first put in a whites-only school in
요하네스버그의 백인 전용 학교에
Johannesburg,
다녔다고 전해집니다.
then in a German language school in Swakopmund,
그 후 스바코프문트의 독일어 학교에 다녔는데,
where their curriculum pushes a Christian nationalist
그곳의 교육과정은 기독교 민족주의 세계관을
worldview and even paints white South Africans as
강조하고 심지어 백인 남아프리카인을
the real victims of the region. This is
이 지역의 진정한 피해자로 그렸습니다. 이곳이
where
바로
Peter Thiel spends formative years. It's a world
피터 틸이 형성기를 보낸 곳입니다. 그의 가족이
where his family benefits from a white supremacist
백인 우월주의 정권의 혜택을 받고
regime,
그의 아버지가
where his father actively advances its military interests.
적극적으로 그 정권의 군사적 이익을 증진시킨 세계입니다.
A world where the founding belief is that
일부 사람들은 지배하도록 되어 있고
some
다수는
people are meant to rule, and the majority
복종해야 한다는 것이 창립 신념인
must serve.
세계입니다.
When Peter is 10, he and his family
피터가 10살 때, 그와 가족은
return to the US. Peter is developing into
미국으로 돌아옵니다. 피터는 전형적인
a classic nerd. He loves
너드로 성장하고 있습니다. 그는 SF와
sci-fi and fantasy, especially Lord of the
판타지를, 특히 반지의 제왕을 좋아합니다.
Rings. He's top of the class and becomes
그는 반에서 1등이고 13세 미만 미국
one of the country's
최고의 체스
top chess players under the age of 13.
선수 중 한 명이 됩니다.
It's not cool to be a nerd in
70년대와 80년대에는 너드가
the 70s and 80s, so Peter is reportedly
멋지지 않았습니다. 그래서 피터는 일상적으로
bullied on the regular. But he knows he's
괴롭힘을 당했다고 전해집니다. 하지만 그는 자신이
smart and going places. His chessboard has a
똑똒하고 앞으로 나아갈 것을 알고 있었습니다. 그의 체스판에는
sticker that says
"이기기 위해 태어났다"라고
born to win. Peter wants the best for
쓰인 스티커가 붙어 있었습니다. 피터는 자신을 위해
himself, so he studies hard to get into
최고를 원했고, 최고의 대학에
the top university.
들어가기 위해 열심히 공부했습니다.
At the time, Stanford is ranked number one
당시 Stanford는 미국에서 1위로
in the US. When he makes it there
평가받았습니다. 그가 1985년에
in 1985, Stanford's a huge
그곳에 입학했을 때, Stanford는 큰
letdown. Peter expects fellow overachievers, but finds a
실망이었습니다. 피터는 동료 우등생들을 기대했지만
party scene instead. He'd rather hit the
파티 문화를 발견했습니다. 그는 마약보다는
books than the bong. And he's once again
책을 더 좋아했습니다. 그리고 그는 다시 한번
teased for being a nerd. According to the
너드라고 놀림을 받았습니다. 저자 맥스 차프킨에 따르면
author Max Chafkin,
그가 괴롭히는 사람으로
many of the students he perceived as bullies
인식한 학생들 중 다수는
also identify as liberals. A connection that reportedly
자유주의자로 자처했습니다. 그에게 남은 연결고리입니다.
sticks with him. We in fact asked Thiel
우리는 실제로 틸에게 직접 물었지만
ourselves, but didn't get a response. Peter developed
응답을 받지 못했습니다. 피터는 레이건을
into a
지지하는
Reagan-supporting conservative. The campus itself feels far
보수주의자로 성장했습니다. 캠퍼스 자체가 그에게는 너무
too left-wing for him. Anti-Reagan and
좌파적으로 느껴졌습니다. 반 레이건과
anti-Apartheid protests are prominent. And Peter starts
반 아파르트헤이트 시위가 두드러졌습니다. 그리고 피터는
to clash with demonstrators. In The Contrarian,
시위대와 충돌하려 했습니다. 『더 컨트래리언』에서,
Chafkin describes how classmates recall at least one
채프킨은 동급생들이 최소 한 번은
instance where Peter defended Apartheid as
피터가 아파르트헤이트를
economically sound. An allegation that Thiel has since
경제적으로 타당하다고 옹호한 사례를 떠올린다고 설명합니다. 이는 틸이 이후
denied. At the time, some defenders of Apartheid
부인한 주장입니다. 당시 아파르트헤이트 옹호자들 일부는
drew on libertarian arguments. Libertarians believe the best
자유지상주의 논리를 끌어다 썼습니다. 자유지상주의자들은 최선의
society maximizes personal
사회란 개인의
and economic freedom while minimizing government control. They
자유와 경제적 자유를 극대화하고 정부 통제를 최소화하는 것이라고 봅니다. 그들은
see free, unregulated markets as the
자유롭고 규제되지 않은 시장이
best way to allocate resources and drive innovation.
자원을 배분하고 혁신을 촉진하는 최선의 방식이라고 봅니다.
More radical libertarians value property rights and
더 급진적인 자유지상주의자들은 재산권과
free markets above basically anything else. Critics say
자유시장을 사실상 그 무엇보다도 우선시합니다. 비평가들은
this leaves little room for values like social
이런 관점이 사회적
justice, which are cast as secondary or even
정의 같은 가치를 부차적이거나 심지어
incompatible with the libertarian definition of freedom.
자유에 대한 자유지상주의적 정의와 양립할 수 없다는 것으로 취급하게 만든다고 말합니다.
From that perspective, Apartheid could be rationalized. South
그런 관점에서라면 아파르트헤이트도 정당화될 수 있습니다. 남
Africa's systematic denial
아프리카의 체계적인
of civil rights was simply the price to
시민권 박탈은 그저
pay for its higher level of wealth than
주변 국가들보다 더 높은 부를
neighboring countries.
누리기 위해 치르는 대가였다는 것입니다.
By Peter's sophomore year, he's known on campus
피터가 2학년이 될 무렵, 그는 캠퍼스에서
as a hardcore libertarian. And though the 80s
강경한 자유지상주의자로 알려져 있었습니다. 그리고 1980년대는
see
학생들이
students increasingly advocate for race and gender equality,
점점 인종과 성별 평등을 옹호하는 것을 보지만
Stanford is not an entirely liberal
Stanford는 완전히 진보적인 기관은
institution. It has a fair share of other
아닙니다. 피터가 있는 동안 상당수의
conservative and libertarian students and faculty members
보수적이고 자유지상주의적인 학생들과 교수들이
during Peter's time there. Still, Shevkin describes Peter
있었습니다. 그래도 차프킨에 따르면 피터는
feeling like he's in the minority and that
자신이 소수파이고 지배적인
the dominant campus culture is hostile to people
캠퍼스 문화가 자신 같은 사람들에게
like him. So he does what he'll keep
적대적이라고 느꼈습니다. 그래서 그는 평생
doing throughout
계속할 일을
his life. He builds a network of like
합니다. 그는 비슷한 생각을 가진
-minded men. The beginnings of a network that
남성들의 네트워크를 구축합니다. 그의 경력 전반에 걸쳐
will support him
그를 지원할 네트워크의
throughout his career. What will later be known
시작입니다. 나중에 이른바 PayPal 마피아로
as the so-called PayPal Mafia.
알려지게 됩니다.
With 11 other conservative men, Peter launches a
11명의 다른 보수적인 남성들과 함께, 피터는
campus newspaper. The Stanford Review aims to stir
캠퍼스 신문을 창간합니다. Stanford Review는
things up. It regularly criticizes campus culture from
물의를 일으키는 것을 목표로 합니다. 유명하게 신랄한
a conservative perspective, with a famously
스타일로 보수적 관점에서
biting style. Throughout Peter's time at Stanford, a
캠퍼스 문화를 정기적으로 비판합니다. 피터가 Stanford에
few pieces especially stirred a pot. Shevkin found
있는 동안 몇몇 기사가 특히 논란을 일으켰습니다. 차프킨은
a
Stanford
few examples in the Stanford archives that he
아카이브에서 몇 가지 사례를 찾았지만
wasn't allowed to reproduce. One columnist claimed that
복제 허가를 받지 못했습니다. 한 칼럼니스트는
gay men engage in unnatural sex. Another complained
게이 남성들이 부자연스러운 성관계를 한다고 주장했습니다. 또 다른 칼럼니스트는
when Stanford considered adding non-white authors to
Stanford가 서양 문화 과목에 비백인
the Western culture course, arguing it signaled the
작가를 추가하려 할 때 불만을 제기했고,
decline of the West. One whole issue was
이것이 서양의 쇠퇴를 의미한다고 주장했습니다. 한 호 전체가
devoted to
법정 강간 혐의를
passionately defending a student accused of statutory rape,
받은 학생을 열정적으로 옹호하는 데 할애되었는데,
who was later found guilty. Peter's not just
그 학생은 나중에 유죄 판결을 받았습니다. 피터는 단순히
looking to provoke. He wants money, power, and
도발하려는 게 아닙니다. 그는 돈, 권력,
influence. And as its founding editor-in-chief,
영향력을 원합니다. 창립 편집장으로서
the Stanford Review launches him into the public
Stanford Review는 그를 오늘날 알려진
intellectual he's known as today.
공적 지식인으로 발돋움시킵니다.
The paper captures the attention of high-profile
이 신문은 유명 보수주의자들의
conservatives, and a bit later Peter gets a
관심을 끌었고, 얼마 후 피터는
book
책 계약을
deal. The diversity myth is co-authored with
따냅니다. 『다양성의 신화』는 데이비드 삭스와
David Sachs, the student who wrote in defense
공동 집필하는데, 그는 Stanford Review에서
of an accused racist in the Stanford Review.
인종차별 혐의를 받은 학생을 옹호한 학생입니다.
Nowadays, Sachs is also an influential figure on
현재 삭스도 미국 우파에서 영향력 있는
the American right. He currently serves the Trump
인물입니다. 그는 현재 트럼프 행정부에서
administration as the White House's AI and
백악관 AI 및 암호화폐 차르로
Crypto Czar. The book argues that universities are
활동하고 있습니다. 이 책은 대학이 좌파
dangerous breeding grounds for left-wing
지적 순응주의의 위험한
intellectual conformity. That nowadays, real racism barely exists
온상이라고 주장합니다. 오늘날 미국에서는 진정한 인종차별이
in America. And that diversity
거의 존재하지 않는다고 합니다. 그리고 다양성
initiatives pose a threat to Western culture. Sachs
이니셔티브는 서양 문화에 위협이 된다고 합니다. 삭스와
and Teal have since apologized for some of
틸은 이후 책의 더 논쟁적인
the more
일부 부분에 대해
controversial parts of the book. But these are
사과했습니다. 하지만 이것들은 오늘날
the same anti-woke sentiments that are winning
선거에서 승리하는 것과 같은 반 워크
elections
정서입니다.
today. Though Peter has plenty of gripes about
피터는 Stanford에 대해 불만이 많지만
Stanford, he stays on and graduates from its
남아서 1992년에 로스쿨을 졸업합니다. 그는
law school in 1992. He moves to New
법조 경력을 시작하기 위해 뉴욕으로 이주합니다. 최고만을
York to begin his legal career. Only aiming
목표로 하는 그의 목표는 대법원
for the best, his goal
서기가 되는 것입니다.
is to clerk for the Supreme Court. He's
그는 최고 성적, 자신만의 영향력 있는 신문,
got top grades, his own influential paper, and
적절한 사람들과의 인맥을
connections to the
갖추고 있습니다.
right people. But it's not enough. I got
하지만 그것으로 충분하지 않았습니다. 저는 두 명의
interviews with two justices. They normally interview eight
대법관과 면접을 봤습니다. 그들은 보통 8명을
people and select four as clerks. And I
면접하고 4명을 서기로 선발합니다. 그런데 저는
missed it with both. And it felt like
둘 다 떨어졌습니다. 그것은 마치
it was the absolute end
세상이 완전히 끝난 것
of the world. Peter's not used to setbacks.
같았습니다. 피터는 좌절에 익숙하지 않습니다.
He plunges into what he later described as
그는 나중에 인생 4분의 1 위기라고
a quarter-life
묘사한 것에
crisis and briefly moves back in with his
빠지고 잠시 부모님 집으로
parents. But back on the West Coast, Peter
돌아갑니다. 하지만 서부 해안으로 돌아온 피터는
proves he has a neck
손실을 큰 승리로 바꾸는
for turning losses into big wins.
재주가 있다는 것을 증명합니다.
It's 1996. The tech industry is booming. Silicon
1996년입니다. 기술 산업이 호황입니다. 실리콘
Valley is a place with endless possibilities,
밸리는 무한한 가능성이 있는 곳입니다,
loads of investor money, and above all, unclear
많은 투자 자금과 무엇보다 불분명한
rules. Peter wants in. Sure, he can't really
규칙이 있습니다. 피터는 들어가고 싶어합니다. 물론 그는
code,
코딩을 못하지만
but he can hand that off on someone
다른 사람에게
else. Peter studies up on hedge fund management,
맡길 수 있습니다. 피터는 헤지펀드 관리를 공부하고
raises some
약간의
capital and reinvents himself as an investor. At
자본을 모으고 투자자로서 자신을 재탄생시킵니다. 한편
the same time, he continues publishing anti-woke
같은 시기에 그는 반(反) 워크 성향의
columns.
칼럼을 계속 게재합니다.
One that claims indigenous people stay as anti
그중 하나는 원주민들이 반
-western winds up in the Wall Street Journal.
서구적 상태로 남아 있다고 주장하는데, 그 글이 월스트리트저널에 실립니다.
By chance, Peter meets the brilliant young cryptographer
우연히 피터는 뛰어난 젊은 암호학자
Max Leftchin. Max is obsessed with
맥스 레브친을 만납니다. 맥스는
Palm Pilots, clunky little handheld computers. At the
팜 파일럿이라는 투박한 소형 휴대용 컴퓨터에 집착합니다. 당시
time, they're barely more than a calendar with
그것은 인터넷 연결이 있는
an
일종의
internet connection. Not all investors would listen to
달력에 가까웠습니다. 모든 투자자가
a 20-something jabber away about Palm Pilots.
스무 살대가 팜 파일럿 얘기를 장황하게 늘어놓는 걸 들어주진 않았을 겁니다.
But Peter is not a typical investor. Max
하지만 피터는 전형적인 투자자가 아닙니다. 맥스는
believes Palm Pilots will have way more potential
팜 파일럿이 훨씬 더 큰 잠재력을 갖게 될 거라고 믿습니다.
if they
그것은
can be linked to businesses. If personal devices
기업과 연결될 수만 있다면 말입니다. 개인 기기가
were linked to a business's infrastructure,
기업의 인프라와 연결된다면,
a whole new world of users would open
완전히 새로운 사용자 세계가 열릴
up. Like connecting an individual directly with a
수 있습니다. 예컨대 개인을
bank.
은행과 직접 연결하는 것처럼요.
All someone needs to figure out is how
누군가가 풀어야 할 것은
to build an encrypted network that can securely
안전하게 작동하는 암호화 네트워크를 구축해
link a
하나의
handheld device with a corporate system. And Max
휴대용 기기와 기업 시스템을 연결할 수 있는 방법뿐입니다. 그리고 맥스는
believes he can do it. He is way
그걸 해낼 수 있다고 믿습니다. 그는
ahead of his time,
시대보다 한참 앞서 있었고,
and Peter sees the potential immediately. He offers
피터는 즉시 그 잠재력을 알아봅니다. 그는
Max a quarter million dollar investment
맥스에게 25만 달러를 투자하겠다고
the very next day. Peter will become known
바로 다음 날 제안합니다. 피터는
for these big bets on inexperienced founders.
경험 없는 창업자들에게 거는 이런 큰 베팅으로 유명해질 겁니다.
Bets that very often pay off.
그리고 그 베팅은 놀랍도록 자주 성공합니다.
On the surface, PayPal looks just like another
겉으로 보면 페이팔은 그저 또 하나의
convenient way to pay. But in reality,
편리한 결제 수단처럼 보입니다. 하지만 실제로는,
it was built on a radically libertarian vision.
급진적 자유지상주의 비전에 기반해 만들어졌습니다.
Money moving freely, beyond government control.
정부 통제를 벗어나 돈이 자유롭게 이동하는 세상입니다.
The same vision that would later drive the
훗날
crypto movement. And just like crypto,
암호화폐 운동을 이끌 비전과 같습니다. 그리고 암호화폐처럼,
that freedom quickly attracts the grey areas of
그 자유는 곧 경제의 회색지대를
the economy.
빠르게 끌어들입니다.
PayPal's early growth comes from industries most banks
페이팔의 초기 성장은 대부분의 은행이
avoided, like gambling and NSFW stuff.
기피하던 도박이나 NSFW 콘텐츠 같은 산업에서 나옵니다.
Good thing Peter's been nurturing his political connections.
다행히도 피터는 정치권 인맥을 꾸준히 다져오고 있었습니다.
As Chafkin tells it,
채프킨의 설명에 따르면,
Thiel worked to keep his business alive by
틸은 사업을 살리기 위해
lobbying congress to keep online gambling legal and
의회에 로비해 온라인 도박을 합법으로 유지하고
to stop
또
PayPal from being treated as a national bank.
페이팔이 국가 은행처럼 취급되는 것을 막으려 했습니다.
We also asked Peter Thiel directly about this,
저희도 이 문제에 대해 피터 틸에게 직접 물었지만,
but didn't get a response either.
답변은 받지 못했습니다.
Ecommerce is exploding in popularity. There's high demand
전자상거래가 폭발적으로 인기를 얻고 있습니다. 이에 따라
for a tool that can simplify online
온라인 거래를 단순화해 줄 도구에 대한 수요가
transaction. And Max and Peter aren't the only
매우 큽니다. 그리고 맥스와 피터만
ones working on a solution. PayPal isn't even
해결책을 찾는 게 아닙니다. 페이팔은
the only
심지어
online payment startup in the same building. There's
같은 건물에 있는 유일한 온라인 결제 스타트업도 아닙니다. 그곳에는
a very similar company on the same floor.
같은 층에 매우 비슷한 회사가 있습니다.
It's called
이름은
x.com and its founder has a lot
X.com이고, 창업자는 피터와
in common with Peter. Most notably, Elon Musk
공통점이 많습니다. 특히 일론 머스크는
is also an enterprising
역시
immigrant with roots in South Africa. Like Peter,
남아프리카에 뿌리를 둔 진취적인 이민자입니다. 피터처럼,
he also shows little regard for traditional rules
그는 전통적인 규칙을
of
별로
the banking industry. Playing by every rule only
은행업계에서는 거의 신경 쓰지 않습니다. 모든 규칙을 따르는 것은
slows down growth. But for a while, they
성장만 늦출 뿐입니다. 하지만 한동안 그들은
have no
서로의
idea what each other's companies are for. Until
회사가 무엇을 하는지 전혀 모릅니다. 그러다
a PayPal employee finds a business plan for
페이팔 직원이
x.com in a
쓰레기통에서 X.com의
dumpster. And then it becomes impossible to ignore
사업 계획서를 발견합니다. 그 뒤로는 서로를 외면할 수 없게
each other. They become two of the biggest
됩니다. 그들은
fish in
가장 큰 두 마리의 물고기가
the sea of online payments. PayPal's growing rapidly,
온라인 결제의 바다에서 헤엄치게 됩니다. 페이팔은 빠르게 성장하지만,
but at the same time bleeding funds.
동시에 자금이 빠져나가고 있습니다.
Every new user gets a cash bonus, most
신규 사용자는 모두 현금 보너스를 받고, 대부분
transactions rack up fees, and servers are expensive.
거래에는 수수료가 붙으며, 서버 비용도 비쌉니다.
Worse,
더 심각한 것은,
the anonymity that makes PayPal attractive also opens
페이팔을 매력적으로 만드는 익명성이
the door to credit card fraud. And PayPal
신용카드 사기의 문도 연다는 점입니다. 그리고 페이팔은
would
그렇게 되면
have to refund the victim's stolen money. Max
피해자의 도난당한 돈을 환불해 줘야 했습니다. 맥스는
left in response by building an anti-fraud
이에 대응해 사기 방지
system called
시스템을 만들었는데
Igor. Software that flags suspicious patterns and blocks
이름은 이고르였습니다. 의심스러운 패턴을 감지해 표시하고
scam transactions. All the while,
사기 거래를 차단하는 소프트웨어입니다. 그와 동시에,
user anonymity is still preserved. Igor successfully curbs
사용자 익명성은 여전히 보장됩니다. 이고르는
fraud by half of what it was. The
사기를 이전의 절반 수준으로 줄이는 데 성공합니다. FBI가
FBI takes
이 기술에
interest in the technology and starts using the
관심을 갖고, 이 소프트웨어를
software to catch money launderers.
자금 세탁범을 잡는 데 쓰기 시작합니다.
Still, PayPal isn't profitable. Peter thinks he knows
그럼에도 페이팔은 수익을 내지 못합니다. 피터는 답을 안다고
the answer. It has to become a monopoly.
생각합니다. 독점이 되어야 한다는 겁니다.
Eliminate competitors, dominate the market, and set the
경쟁자를 제거하고, 시장을 지배하고, 규칙을
rules.
정하는 겁니다.
As Peter often puts it. Competition is for
피터가 자주 말하듯, 경쟁은
losers. Competition is for losers.
패배자들의 몫입니다. 경쟁은 패배자들의 몫입니다. 경쟁은 패배자들의 몫입니다.
Competition is for losers. This strategy will come
이 전략은
to define Peter Thiel's success.
피터 틸의 성공을 규정하게 됩니다.
He'll outline it in the business bestselling book
그는 이를 비즈니스 베스트셀러인
Zero to One. And it will become a
『Zero to One』에서 설명할 것이며, 그것은
guiding
기술 산업의
principle in the tech industry. What I think
지도 원칙이 됩니다. 제가 생각하기에
everybody who is a founder or entrepreneur should
창업자나 기업가라면 누구나
aim to do is build a monopoly. And
독점을 구축하는 것을 목표로 해야 합니다. 그리고
all the great companies that people have built
사람들이 세운 모든 위대한 기업은
are monopolies of one
어떤 형태로든 독점입니다.
sort or another. By 2000, the online payment
2000년이 되자 온라인 결제
space has grown more competitive. And PayPal is
시장은 더 경쟁적으로 변했고, 페이팔은
still
여전히
operating at a loss. Elon suggests a merger.
적자를 내며 운영되고 있습니다. 일론은 합병을 제안합니다.
And Peter agrees. Uniting is their best chance
피터도 동의합니다. 힘을 합치는 것이
for survival.
살아남을 최선의 기회입니다.
According to The Contrarian, they clash from the
『The Contrarian』에 따르면, 그들은 처음부터
start. Over the name. Over the software.
충돌합니다. 이름 문제로, 소프트웨어 문제로요.
Elon becomes CEO because he's a bigger shareholder.
일론은 더 큰 주주이기 때문에 CEO가 됩니다.
But Peter allegedly can't stand his leadership.
하지만 피터는 그의 리더십을 견디지 못했다고 전해집니다.
He's set to think Elon's a reckless egomaniac.
피터는 일론을 무모한 자기애적 인물로 여깁니다.
And Elon is set to think Peter's a
반대로 일론은 피터를
sociopath who
돈만 생각하는 소시오패스라고 여깁니다. 그들의 싸움은
only cares about money. Their battles stall the
돈만 신경 씁니다.
company's growth. So Thiel decides to end them.
그들의 다툼이 회사 성장을 가로막자, 틸은 끝내기로 결심합니다.
Elon goes on his honeymoon, leaving the CEO
일론은 신혼여행을 떠납니다.
position undefended. And in an elegant,
CEO 자리는 무방비가 됩니다. 그리고 우아하고,
calculated move, Peter captures it. Levchin and others
계산된 한 수로 피터가 그 자리를 차지합니다. 레브친과 다른 이들이
loyal to Thiel start voicing their
틸에게 충성하던 사람들은
gripes about Musk. They manage to convince enough
머스크에 대한 불만을 표하기 시작합니다.
board members to oust Musk and to insert
그들은 이사회 구성원을 충분히 설득합니다.
Thiel as
그리고 머스크를 축출한 뒤,
temporary CEO. A position he'll keep. It won't
틸을 임시 CEO로 앉힙니다. 그는 그 자리를 계속 맡게 됩니다. 이것은
be Thiel's last tactical takedown.
틸의 마지막 전술적 제거가 아닐 것입니다.
As CEO of PayPal, Peter Thiel is on
페이팔 CEO가 된 피터 틸은 완전히 새로운 무대에 섭니다.
a whole new playing field. In 2002, he
2002년, 그는 중요한 전환점을 맞습니다.
secures a landmark deal.
그는 획기적인 거래를 성사시킵니다.
eBay acquires PayPal for 1.5 billion dollars.
이베이가 15억 달러에 페이팔을 인수합니다.
Thiel becomes a multi-millionaire at 35 years
틸은 35세에 수백만 달러 자산가가 됩니다.
old,
그리고 그 거래로도 큰돈을 벌어들입니다.
walking away with at least 55 million dollars
그 금액은 최소 5,500만 달러입니다.
from the deal. Now he has the capital
그 돈을 챙겨 떠납니다. 이제 그는 자본을
and credibility
갖추고 신뢰도도 얻게 됩니다.
to pursue his wildest dreams. The day he
그래서 그는 가장 대담한 꿈을 추구할 수 있게 됩니다.
signs the deal is the day he also
그는 그 거래에 서명합니다.
steps down as CEO.
그리고 같은 날 CEO 자리에서 물러납니다.
PayPal was just a stepping stone. Now he's
페이팔은 그저 디딤돌이었습니다.
ready to move on to bigger and bolder
이제 그는 더 크고 대담한 프로젝트로 옮겨갈 준비가 됩니다.
projects. And to
그리고 초부유층으로서 호화로운 삶도 누립니다.
live the high life as a very rich
그는 은색 페라리를 삽니다.
person. He buys a silver Ferrari and fancy
그리고 고급 아파트도 삽니다.
apartments. Now the
이제 한때 괴롭힘을 당하던 아이가
formerly bullied kid is the life of the
파티의 주인공이 됩니다. 점점 더 많은 사람들이
party. More and more people want to be
그의 주변에 있고 싶어 합니다.
in his orbit. Thiel's
틸의 개인적 상승세는 치솟습니다.
personal trajectory is skyrocketing. But the country is
하지만 나라는 흔들리고 있습니다.
spiraling.
나락으로 빠져듭니다.
In the wake of 9-11, Americans also
9·11 이후 미국인들도
face a recession, an unpopular war and widespread
경기 침체와 인기 없는 전쟁, 그리고 광범위한
trauma.
트라우마에 직면합니다.
Thiel is anxious too. He's increasingly concerned with
틸 역시 불안해합니다. 그는 점점 더
the threat of religious terrorism.
종교적 테러의 위협을 우려합니다.
He finds the Bush administration isn't tough enough
그는 부시 행정부가 충분히 강경하지
on Islam. His politics seem to shift. At
않다고 봅니다. 그의 정치 성향이 바뀌는 듯합니다.
Stanford he wrote fiery libertarian essays railing against
스탠퍼드에서 그는 정부 권력을 비판하는 격렬한 자유지상주의 글을 썼습니다.
government power. Now he's arguing the
하지만 이제 그는 정반대를 주장합니다.
opposite, that the US must use extra judicial
미국은 테러리스트를 잡기 위해 초법적
methods to catch terrorists. As he put it,
방법을 써야 한다는 것입니다. 그의 말로는,
outside the checks and balances of representative democracy
고등학교 교과서에 나오는 대의민주주의의 견제와 균형 밖에서
as described in high school textbooks.
해야 한다는 것입니다.
For Thiel, the trade-off is clear. The
틸에게 그 대가는 분명합니다.
West must compromise. More security, less freedom. And
서방은 타협해야 합니다. 더 많은 안보, 더 적은 자유입니다.
he
틸은 그 점을 이용합니다.
sees a business opportunity in it. What if
그 안에서 사업 기회를 봅니다. 만약
Igor, the software Max Levchin built to catch
맥스 레브친이 사기꾼을 잡기 위해 만든 소프트웨어 ‘이고르’를
fraudsters,
사기꾼이 아니라,
could be retooled to catch terrorists? Wouldn't the
테러리스트를 잡도록 개조할 수 있다면 어떨까요? 그러면
CIA be interested? In 2003, Thiel gets a
CIA가 관심을 갖지 않겠습니까? 2003년에 틸은
team to start
한 팀을 꾸려
working on it right away. They'll call the
곧바로 작업을 시작하게 합니다. 회사 이름은
company Palantir. In The Lord of the Rings,
팔란티르라고 짓습니다. 『반지의 제왕』에서,
a Palantir is a mythical stone that sees
팔란티르는 멀리까지 보고
and communicates across far distances. Sauron,
소통할 수 있는 신화 속 돌입니다. 사우론은
the evil character who seeks to dominate Middle
중간계를 지배하려는 악역으로,
-earth, uses a Palantir to spy on enemies
팔란티르를 이용해 적을 염탐하고
and conspire with
동맹과
allies. Basically, Thiel is offering Sauron's power to
모의를 합니다. 요컨대 틸은 사우론의 힘을
anyone who can afford it. Palantir's promise?
돈을 낼 수 있는 누구에게나 파는 셈입니다. 팔란티르의 약속은 무엇일까요?
Use network analysis to find unforeseen patterns in
네트워크 분석을 이용해 예상치 못한 패턴을 찾아내는 것입니다.
vast troughs of data. This is especially interesting
방대한 데이터의 심연에서요. 이는 특히
to US intelligence agencies who had collected information
알카에다 공모자들에 대한 정보를 모아 두고도 연결을 못 본 미국 정보기관에
on Al-Qaeda conspirators but failed
특히 흥미롭습니다.
to see the connections till after the attack.
그들은 공격 이후에야 비로소 연결고리를 보았기 때문입니다.
In the early years, many users are disappointed
초기에는 많은 이용자들이
with
팔란티르 서비스에
Palantir's service. But their timing is excellent with
실망합니다. 하지만 모두가 또 다른 공격을 두려워하던 시기라 타이밍은 훌륭했습니다.
everyone terrified of another attack. And Thiel's
그리고 틸이
chosen CEO is excellent at raising money. His
선택한 CEO는 자금 조달에 탁월합니다. 그의
name is Alex Karp. He's another former Stanford
이름은 알렉스 카프이며, 또 다른 전 스탠퍼드
classmate.
동문입니다.
When Osama Bin Laden is captured and killed,
오사마 빈 라덴이 붙잡혀 사살되자,
rumors circulate that Palantir was used to find
그를 찾아내는 데 팔란티르가 사용됐다는 소문이
him.
퍼집니다.
Public interest in the company skyrockets. Based on
회사에 대한 대중의 관심은 급등합니다. 그러나
what's known today about Palantir's
현재 알려진 당시 팔란티르의
abilities at the time, any meaningful involvement is
역량을 보면, 실질적인 관여가 있었다는 주장은
questionable. When media outlets ask Alex
의문스럽습니다. 언론이 알렉스
Karp about that rumor, he's careful not to
카프에게 그 소문을 묻자, 그는 조심스럽게
confirm or deny involvement. He tends to dodge
관여 여부를 인정도 부인도 하지 않습니다. 그는 대개
the question
미소를 지으며 질문을
with a smile and imply that some connection
피하면서도, 어딘가 연결이 있는 듯 암시합니다. 귀사에서 추적에
is there. Did your company help to track
도움을 줬고
and kill
사살하는 데에도
Osama Bin Laden?
오사마 빈 라덴을요?
When you open the paper and look in
신문을 펼쳐 이런 종류의
the news about these kinds of things, there's
뉴스를 보면,
a two-thirds chance,
사건에 따라 3분의 2 확률로,
depending on the country involved, that somehow my
어떤 나라가 관련됐느냐에 따라 다르지만 제 회사가 어딘가
company was involved.
관여했을 가능성이 있습니다.
One media outlet isn't buying the hype. A
한 매체는 이 과장에 속지 않습니다.
gossipy blog called Gawker. According to Max Chafkin,
가커라는 가십성 블로그입니다. 맥스 차프킨에 따르면,
Gawker's Silicon Valley page reports no real link
가커의 실리콘밸리 페이지는 팔란티르와 빈 라덴 급습 사이에 실질적인 연관이
between Palantir and the Bin Laden raid,
없다고 보도했고,
and suggests the company spread the rumor just
회사가 매출을 끌어올리려고 그 소문을 퍼뜨렸다고 시사합니다.
to boost sales. Valleyweg is known for roasting
밸리왜그는 대부분의 언론이
the
기술 업계를
tech industry back when most news outlets tend
찬양하던 시절에도 이를 신랄하게 조롱하는 것으로 알려져 있습니다.
to sing its praises. And a favorite target
그리고 가커가 즐겨 겨냥한 표적
of Gawker's
중 하나는 피터 틸입니다.
gossip and mockery is Peter Thiel. Thiel will
틸은
take care of Gawker later.
나중에 가커를 처리하게 됩니다.
Beyond founding Palantir, Thiel spends the 2000s turning
팔란티르를 창업한 것 외에도, 틸은 2000년대에
tech startups into giants.
기술 스타트업을 거대 기업으로 키우는 데 시간을 씁니다.
I was the sort of first angel investor
저는 2004년 여름, 페이스북에 투자한 사실상 첫 엔젤 투자자였습니다.
in Facebook in the summer of 2004. The
그때 사업은 이미
business was already
상당히 잘 돌아가고 있었습니다.
tracking quite well. They only needed money to
그들은 돈이 더 필요했는데,
buy more computers, so I think that was
컴퓨터를 더 사기 위해서였습니다. 그래서 저는 그것이
always sort of
언제나 일종의
a promising sign.
유망한 신호라고 생각했습니다.
In 2004, he becomes Facebook's first big investor.
2004년에 그는 페이스북의 첫 대형 투자자가 됩니다.
Thiel not only funds the company,
틸은 그 회사에 자금을 댈 뿐만 아니라,
but becomes Zuckerberg's mentor. Now, Zuckerberg is one
저커버그의 멘토가 되기도 합니다. 이제 저커버그는
of the richest people alive. And Thiel's
현존하는 가장 부유한 사람들 중 한 명입니다. 그리고 틸의
investment will net him about $400 million. Thiel
투자는 그에게 약 4억 달러를 안겨줄 것입니다.
doesn't stop there. Through his network,
틸은 거기서 멈추지 않습니다. 그는 자신의 네트워크를 통해
he backs Airbnb, Spotify, SpaceX, and later OpenAI.
에어비앤비, 스포티파이, 스페이스X, 그리고 이후 오픈AI에도 투자합니다.
In 2007, Thiel seems to have spotted the
2007년에 틸은 금융 위기를 일찍 포착한 듯합니다.
financial crisis early. He bets against the US
그는 미국
housing market. The gamble pays off.
주택시장에 반대로 베팅합니다. 그 도박은 성공합니다.
A 60% return in just six months.
단 6개월 만에 60% 수익률입니다.
Banks will collapse, and around 9 million Americans
은행들이 붕괴하고, 약 900만 명의 미국인이
will
결국
lose their jobs. But for Thiel, it's cause
일자리를 잃게 됩니다. 하지만 틸에게는 이는
for celebration. According to Chavkin, he flies his
축하할 일입니다. 차프킨에 따르면, 그는
stuff to Maui, with unlimited tabs for food,
짐을 마우이로 보내고, 음식에
booze, massages, and surfing. We asked Peter Thiel
술, 마사지, 서핑까지 무제한으로 돈을 씁니다. 우리는 피터 틸에게
if this
이것이
is true, but he didn't answer. But Thiel's
사실인지 물었지만, 그는 답하지 않았습니다. 그러나 틸의
golden run doesn't last. After a string of
황금기는 오래가지 않습니다. 연이은
bad investments and
잘못된 투자와
mass redemptions, his hedge fund suffers huge losses
대규모 환매로 인해 그의 헤지펀드는 막대한 손실을
and all but collapses. By 2011, he will
입고 사실상 붕괴합니다. 2011년까지 그는
have lost nearly two-thirds of his clients'
고객 돈의 거의 3분의 2를
money. The crisis seems to make Thiel more
잃게 됩니다. 이 위기는 틸을 더
cynical. In 2009,
냉소적으로 만든 듯합니다. 2009년에,
he writes that he still believes in libertarian
그는 자유지상주의
principles, but no longer in democracy.
원칙은 여전히 믿지만, 민주주의는 더 이상 믿지 않는다고 씁니다.
I no longer believe that freedom and democracy
“저는 더 이상 자유와 민주주의가
are compatible, he declares. He argues that America
양립한다고 믿지 않습니다.”라고 그는 선언합니다. 그는 미국이
has
여성들이
been in decline since the 1920s, when women
투표권을 얻은 1920년대부터 쇠퇴해 왔다고 주장하며,
gained the right to vote, and when the
또한
Great Depression
대공황이
created mass unemployment. In his view, women and
대규모 실업을 만들었다고 말합니다. 그의 시각에서 여성과
poor people are especially hostile to libertarian
가난한 사람들은 특히 자유지상주의
policies. Their ability to vote stands in the
정책에 적대적입니다. 그들의 투표권은
way of his ideal society.
그가 이상으로 여기는 사회를 가로막는다고 봅니다.
The essay makes waves. Gawker Media calls him
그 에세이는 큰 파장을 일으킵니다. 가커 미디어는 그를
a loopy libertarian, ridiculing him for wishing women
‘괴상한 자유지상주의자’라고 부르며 여성이
couldn't vote. Thiel later clarifies it's not that
투표하지 못하길 바란다고 조롱합니다. 틸은 나중에 이것이
he wants to take one class of voters'
어떤 한 계층 유권자의
rights away.
권리를 빼앗고 싶다는 뜻은 아니라고 해명합니다.
The problem is that Americans, in general, won't
문제는 미국인들이 전반적으로
vote for libertarian policies.
자유지상주의 정책에 투표하지 않는다는 점입니다.
So, better to do away with democracy altogether?
그렇다면 민주주의 자체를 없애는 편이 낫지 않을까요?
Meanwhile, Gawker Media gleefully reports Thiel's investment failures.
한편 가커 미디어는 틸의 투자 실패를 신나게 보도합니다.
They claim he exaggerates his net worth and
그들은 그가 자신의 순자산을 과장한다고 주장하며
make fun of his hypocrisies.
그의 위선을 조롱합니다.
Gawker reported on a lot of important topics
가커는 많은 중요한 주제도 보도했습니다.
other media outlets wouldn't touch
다른 언론이 훨씬 나중에야 다루게 되는 것들인데,
till much later, like the crimes of Harvey
하비 와인스타인과 제프리 엡스타인의
Weinstein and Jeffrey Epstein.
범죄 같은 이야기들입니다.
But they also posted a lot of arguably
하지만 그들은 또, 잔인하다고도 할 수 있는
cruel gossip.
가십도 많이 올렸습니다.
In 2007, they outed Thiel's sexual orientation with
2007년, 그들은 제목이
a post titled,
다음과 같은 글로 틸의 성적 지향을 폭로합니다.
Peter Thiel is totally gay people. Peter Thiel's
“피터 틸은 완전 게이입니다, 여러분.” 피터 틸의
sexuality was an open secret at the time,
성적 지향은 당시 공공연한 비밀이었지만,
but he didn't seem to want it reported.
그는 보도되길 원하지 않는 듯했습니다.
His outing was clearly a violation of privacy.
그의 아우팅은 명백히 사생활 침해였습니다.
According to The Contrarian, Thiel sees Gawker's coverage
『더 콘트래리언』에 따르면, 틸은 가커의 보도가
as damaging to his business.
자신의 사업에 해가 된다고 봅니다.
And plenty of other people have grudges against
또한 가커에 원한을 가진 사람들이
the side,
많았기 때문에,
so Thiel quietly funds a team of lawyers
틸은 조용히 변호사 팀에 자금을 대어
to take up their cases.
그들의 소송을 맡게 합니다.
The decisive moment comes in 2012, when Gawker
결정적인 순간은 2012년에 찾아오는데, 가커가 유출된
publishes a leaked
프로 레슬러 헐크 호건의
sex tape of the wrestler Hulk Hogan. Hogan
성관계 동영상을 공개했기 때문입니다. 호건은
sues, and Thiel secretly
소송을 제기하고, 틸은 비밀리에
bankrolls the fight with $10 million.
1,000만 달러로 그 싸움을 지원합니다.
The stage is set for a major courtroom
이로써 대규모 법정
battle.
싸움의 무대가 마련됩니다.
Hulk Hogan, former professional wrestler turned reality star,
전 프로 레슬러이자 리얼리티 스타가 된 헐크 호건이,
is taking on media website Gawker.
미디어 웹사이트 가커와 맞섭니다.
Gawker is hit with just over $140 million
가커는 1억 4,000만 달러가 조금 넘는
in damages and files for bankruptcy in 2016.
손해배상 판결을 받고, 2016년에 파산을 신청합니다.
Gawker Media is no more. And Thiel is
가커 미디어는 더 이상 존재하지 않습니다. 그리고 틸은
proud of his win,
자신의 승리를 자랑스러워하며,
calling it the most philanthropic thing he's ever
그것을 자신이 한 일 중 가장 자선적인 일이라고
done.
말합니다.
In an interview, he compares the journalists behind
한 인터뷰에서 그는 그 회사의 기자들을
the company to terrorists.
테러리스트에 비유합니다.
The world learned that it's dangerous to mess
세상은 피터 틸과
with Peter Thiel.
맞서는 것이 위험하다는 사실을 배웁니다.
Reporters Without Borders called his feet a serious
국경 없는 기자회는 그의 행동이 심각한
threat on freedom of the press.
언론의 자유에 대한 위협이라고 했습니다.
Critics argue that this set a precedent for
비평가들은 이것이 부유한 개인들이
wealthy individuals to
법원을
weaponize the courts and bury media that criticizes
무기화해 자신을 비판하는 언론을
them.
매장할 수 있게 만드는 선례가 됐다고 주장합니다.
But Peter Thiel is just getting started.
그러나 피터 틸은 이제 막 시작했을 뿐입니다.
It's often said that two things in life
인생에서 확실한 것은 두 가지뿐이라고들 합니다.
are certain, death and taxes.
바로 죽음과 세금입니다.
Well, Peter Thiel disagrees.
하지만 피터 틸은 이에 동의하지 않습니다.
With others see as inevitabilities, Thiel sees as
다른 이들이 피할 수 없는 운명이라 여기는 것들도 틸은
problems to be solved.
해결해야 할 문제로 봅니다.
He famously funds biotech companies pursuing life extension.
그는 수명 연장을 추구하는 바이오테크 기업들에 유명하게도 자금을 댑니다.
His hatred of taxes has some poor resources
세금에 대한 그의 혐오감은 막대한 자원을 쏟아붓게 했고
into anti-tax political actions and also seasteading.
반(反)세금 정치 활동과 시스테딩에도 이어졌습니다.
Man-made island nations free from income tax
소득세에서 자유로운 인공 섬나라,
and governmental regulations.
그리고 정부 규제에서도 자유로운 나라입니다.
A floating libertarian utopia where he can escape
그가 도망칠 수 있는 떠다니는 자유지상주의 유토피아로,
systems he finds oppressive.
그가 억압적이라고 여기는 체제들로부터 벗어나는 곳입니다.
An idea he has since abandoned.
하지만 그는 이후 그 생각을 버립니다.
He looks into other exit plans, like a
그는 뉴질랜드의
bunker in New Zealand, which he also later
벙커 같은 다른 탈출 계획도 살펴보지만, 이것도 나중에는
drops.
포기합니다.
And the chance for humanity to reach Mars.
그리고 인류가 화성에 도달할 가능성도요.
This becomes Peter Thiel's pattern.
이것이 피터 틸의 패턴이 됩니다.
Seeking escape.
탈출을 추구하는 것입니다.
Escape from rules that govern everyone else.
다른 모두를 지배하는 규칙들로부터의 탈출입니다.
But escape on Peter Thiel's scale doesn't come
하지만 피터 틸 규모의 탈출은
easily.
쉽게 이루어지지 않습니다.
Immortality research and space exploration require massive resources.
불로 연구와 우주 탐사는 막대한 자원이 필요합니다.
Changing tax laws requires massive influence.
세법을 바꾸려면 막대한 영향력이 필요합니다.
Fortunately for Thiel,
틸에게 다행히도,
his wealth and influence have grown enormously.
그의 부와 영향력은 엄청나게 커졌습니다.
So he can attempt to reshape politics to
그래서 그는 정치를 재편해
enable his search for escape.
자신의 탈출을 가능하게 하려 합니다.
In 2007, he does something unusual for Silicon
2007년, 그는 실리콘밸리
Valley entrepreneurs.
기업가로서는 이례적인 일을 합니다.
He starts funding presidential candidates.
대통령 후보들에게 자금을 대기 시작한 것입니다.
His first big bet is the libertarian Ron
그의 첫 큰 베팅은 자유지상주의자 론
Paul.
폴이었습니다.
A longshot candidate for presidency, but a politician
당선 가능성은 낮았지만, 정치인이었고
with a passionate base.
열성적인 지지층을 갖고 있었습니다.
Like Thiel, Paul is an advocate for extreme
틸처럼 폴도 극단적인
free market capitalism.
자유시장 자본주의를 옹호합니다.
They're also both skeptical of climate change to
또 두 사람 모두 기후변화에 회의적이기도 한데
different degrees.
정도만 다를 뿐입니다.
Ron Paul doesn't win the 2008 presidency.
론 폴은 2008년 대선에서 승리하지 못합니다.
Obama does.
오바마가 승리합니다.
In 2012, Ron Paul runs again.
2012년, 론 폴은 다시 출마합니다.
And this time, Thiel is his biggest donor
그리고 이번에는 틸이
by a longshot.
압도적으로 가장 큰 후원자였습니다.
Thiel wasn't really banking on Paul's win.
틸은 폴의 승리에 크게 기대한 것은 아니었습니다.
Instead, he was thinking ahead.
대신 그는 더 앞을 내다보고 있었습니다.
In an interview with the magazine Slate from
2012년, 잡지 슬레이트와의 인터뷰에서
2012, Thiel says he was really campaigning for
틸은 자신이 사실상 2016년을 위해
2016.
선거운동을 하고 있었다고 말합니다.
Building up a strong libertarian base.
강력한 자유지상주의 기반을 구축하는 것이었습니다.
Thiel seems to want a candidate who will
틸은 자신의 부가 보호되도록 해줄 후보를 원하는 듯합니다.
ensure his wealth will be protected.
자신의 재산이 안전하도록 보장해줄 인물입니다.
One who will grant more power to the
기술 산업에
tech industry.
더 많은 권력을 부여할 인물입니다.
And one who shares his view that America
그리고 미국이 쇠퇴하고 있으며
is in decline and needs a strong man
다시 위대해지려면 강한 지도자가 필요하다는
to become great again.
그의 관점을 공유하는 인물입니다.
When Trump is revealed as the best candidate
그 목표를 추진하기에 트럼프가
to promote those aims,
가장 적합한 후보로 드러나자,
Thiel donates $1.25 million to his campaign.
틸은 그의 선거운동에 125만 달러를 기부합니다.
In 2016, Thiel takes the stage at the
2016년, 틸은 공화당 전당대회
Republican National Convention during primetime.
프라임타임에 연단에 오릅니다.
Tonight, I urge all of my fellow Americans
오늘 밤, 저는 모든 미국 동료 시민 여러분께
to stand up and vote for Donald Trump.
일어나 도널드 트럼프에게 투표해 달라고 촉구합니다.
Thiel campaigns for Trump as if his views
틸은 트럼프를 위해 선거운동을 하며, 그의 견해가
represented Silicon Valley.
실리콘밸리를 대표하는 것처럼 행동합니다.
But at the time, Trump is deeply unpopular
하지만 당시 트럼프는 기술 업계에서
in tech.
극도로 인기가 없었습니다.
Of the top tech companies in the Valley,
밸리의 주요 기술 기업들 가운데
not a single CEO donates to Trump's 2016
트럼프의 2016년 선거운동에
campaign.
기부한 CEO는 단 한 명도 없었습니다.
And Thiel's support of Trump makes him somewhat
틸의 트럼프 지지는 그를 어느 정도
of a pariah.
왕따 같은 존재로 만들었습니다.
According to the contrarian, friends cut ties with
『더 콘트라리언』에 따르면, 친구들은 그와
him or refuse to discuss politics.
관계를 끊거나 정치 이야기를 거부했습니다.
Thiel is unbothered.
틸은 개의치 않습니다.
They'll change their tune soon enough.
곧 태도를 바꿀 것이라고 생각합니다.
Besides, he's starting to lean into his image
게다가 그는 실리콘밸리의 슈퍼빌런이라는
as the Silicon Valley supervillain.
이미지를 점점 받아들이기 시작합니다.
He reportedly once said,
그는 한때 이렇게 말했다고 전해집니다.
I'd rather be seen as evil than incompetent.
무능해 보이느니 차라리 악인으로 보이겠습니다.
When Trump shocks the world by winning, Thiel
트럼프가 세상을 놀라게 하며 승리하자, 틸은
is part of the transition team.
인수위원회에 합류합니다.
His role is to appoint people who will
그의 역할은 연방거래위원회나
disrupt regulatory bodies like the Federal Trade
식품의약국 같은 규제 기관을
Commission and the Food and Drug Administration.
흔들 인물들을 임명하는 것이었습니다.
A dream job for Thiel, who's railed against
수십 년간 정부 규제를 비판해온 틸에게는
governmental regulation for decades.
꿈의 직업이었습니다.
Thiel reportedly suggests 150 names to Trump.
틸은 트럼프에게 150명의 이름을 제안했다고 전해집니다.
According to Max Shevkin, his list includes, to
맥스 차프킨에 따르면, 그의 명단에는 예상대로
no surprise, ultra-libertarians.
극단적 자유지상주의자들이 포함되어 있었습니다.
But also very controversial figures.
하지만 매우 논란이 큰 인물들도 있었습니다.
Fringe people from his growing network of far
그가 키워온 극우 반동 네트워크의
-right reactionaries.
주변부 인물들이었습니다.
Trump only approves a handful of them.
트럼프는 그중 소수만 승인합니다.
The least controversial suggestions that Thiel makes.
틸이 제안한 것들 가운데 가장 덜 논란적인 인물들이었습니다.
So Thiel's first attempt at capturing the White
그래서 백악관을 장악하려는 틸의 첫 시도는
House seems to have failed.
실패한 듯 보입니다.
Politically, Thiel retreats to the background for a
정치적으로 틸은 한동안
bit.
배경으로 물러섭니다.
He and his partner have their first child
그와 그의 파트너는 첫 아이를 낳고
and he seems to focus on family life
그는 잠시 가족 생활에
for a while.
집중하는 듯합니다.
But the background is where Peter Thiel thrives
하지만 배후야말로 피터 틸이
the most.
가장 잘 활약하는 자리입니다.
Outside of politics, Thiel's businesses are skyrocketing.
정치 밖에서 틸의 사업들은 급성장하고 있습니다.
Especially Palantir.
특히 팔란티어가 그렇습니다.
During COVID, Palantir wins government contracts to analyze
코로나19 기간 동안 팔란티어는 팬데믹 데이터를 분석하는 정부 계약을 따내
pandemic data,
그 데이터를 분석하며,
tracking infections and vaccines.
감염과 백신을 추적합니다.
In 2025, Business Insider reports that under the
2025년, 비즈니스 인사이더는
second Trump administration,
트럼프 2기 행정부 하에서
ICE will use Palantir to track down immigrants
ICE가 비자를 초과 체류한 이민자들을 추적하는 데
who overstate their visas.
팔란티어를 사용할 것이라고 보도합니다.
Palantir's involvement has only intensified under Trump and
트럼프 하에서 팔란티어의 개입은 더욱 강화되었고
has been instrumental for over a decade
10년이 넘는 기간 동안 핵심적이었습니다.
since Obama's second administration.
오바마 2기 행정부 때부터입니다.
The Guardian reports in 2025 that Palantir provides
가디언은 2025년에 팔란티어가
ICE with tools that help their agents
ICE에 도구를 제공해 요원들이
fulfill Trump's aggressive deportation quotas using a vast
방대한 데이터 네트워크를 활용해 트럼프의 공격적인 추방 할당량을
data network.
달성하도록 돕는다고 보도합니다.
It includes government records such as text data
그 네트워크에는 IRS의 텍스트 데이터 같은
from the IRS and private databases
정부 기록과 민간 데이터베이스가 포함되며
like location history from cell phone records.
예를 들어 휴대전화 기록의 위치 이력 같은 것들입니다.
Now Palantir also incorporates facial recognition data from
이제 팔란티어는 클리어뷰 AI의
Clearview AI,
안면 인식 데이터도 통합하는데,
another startup where Peter Thiel is the first
피터 틸이 최초로 투자한
investor.
또 다른 스타트업입니다.
The pattern is clear.
패턴은 분명합니다.
Palantir thrives in chaos.
팔란티어는 혼란 속에서 성장합니다.
And chaos is only ramping up.
그리고 혼란은 더 커지고 있을 뿐입니다.
What looks like a political setback with Trump
트럼프와 함께한 정치적 좌절로 보이는 일이
may just be Thiel's chance to plan his
오히려 틸이 다음 수를
next move.
계획할 기회일지도 모릅니다.
Thiel won't back Trump's second campaign, but he
틸은 트럼프의 두 번째 대선 캠페인을 지지하지 않겠지만
will build up another politician.
다른 정치인을 키워 올릴 것입니다.
We're effectively run in this country via the
이 나라는 사실상 민주당과
Democrats, via our corporate oligarchs,
기업 과두 세력에 의해 운영되고 있으며,
by a bunch of childless cat ladies who
아이 없는 '고양이 애호가' 여성들이
are miserable at their own lives and the
자신의 삶과 선택에 불만을 품고
choices that they've made.
불행해하고 있기 때문입니다.
Thiel injects J.D. Vance's primary campaign with
틸은 J.D. 밴스의 예비선거 캠페인에
$15 million.
1,500만 달러를 투입합니다.
Vance is now Vice President of the United
밴스는 이제 미국의
States.
부통령입니다.
Thiel and Vance's relationship didn't come out of
틸과 밴스의 관계는
nowhere.
갑자기 생긴 것이 아닙니다.
Vance worked at one of Thiel's companies and
밴스는 틸의 회사 중 한 곳에서 일했고
Thiel became his mentor, as Vance himself says.
밴스 본인의 말처럼 틸은 그의 멘토가 되었습니다.
And it was also Thiel who brought J
그리고 J.D. 밴스와 도널드 트럼프를
.D. Vance and Donald Trump together.
이어준 사람도 틸이었습니다.
After Trump is elected as president again in
트럼프가 2024년에 다시 대통령으로 선출된 뒤,
2024, several members of the tech elite rally
기술 엘리트들 가운데 몇몇이
behind him.
그를 중심으로 결집합니다.
There's Elon Musk, who is against Trump in
2016년에는 트럼프에 반대했지만 2024년에는 가장 눈에 띄는 지지자가 된
2016 and becomes his most visible supporter in
일론 머스크가 있고,
2024.
또한 그가 있습니다.
There's Mark Zuckerberg, who abolishes fact-checkers at
트럼프가 취임하기 2주도 되지 않아 메타에서 팩트체커를 없앤
Meta less than two weeks before Trump takes
마크 저커버그가 있으며
office.
그도 포함됩니다.
And there's Sundar Pekai, the CEO of Google,
그리고 구글 CEO 선다르 피차이는
who donates $1 million to Trump just before
취임 직전에 트럼프에게 100만 달러를 기부합니다.
inauguration.
바로 취임을 앞두고서 말입니다.
At the inauguration of Trump's second presidency in
2025년 1월 트럼프 2기 대통령 취임식에서는
January 2025, major tech CEOs are clearly visible
주요 기술 기업 CEO들이
in the front row.
앞줄에 뚜렷이 보입니다.
Instead, he watches Palantir's stock skyrocket and topping
그 대신 그는 팔란티어 주가가 급등해
the market for much of 2025.
2025년의 상당 기간 시장 상단을 차지하는 것을 지켜봅니다.
The surge is in part fueled by government
그 급등은 부분적으로 정부
contracts.
계약에 의해 촉발됩니다.
Palantir has been hired by Israeli forces allegedly
팔란티어는 이스라엘군에 의해 고용되어
to enable AI power targeting of Palestinians, which
팔레스타인인을 대상으로 한 AI 기반 표적 선정에 쓰였다는 의혹이 있지만 회사는 부인하며,
the company denies, and by Ukraine in its
우크라이나도
war against Russia.
러시아와의 전쟁에서 그 회사를 고용했습니다.
These and other contracts not only boost Palantir's
이런 계약들은 팔란티어의 수익을 늘릴 뿐 아니라
profits, they also give the company access to
회사가 극도로 민감한 데이터에
extremely sensitive data.
접근할 수 있게 합니다.
Few assets carry more power or more potential
이보다 더 큰 권력과
for harm.
더 큰 해악의 가능성을 지닌 자산은 드뭅니다.
So, who decides how it's used?
그렇다면 누가 그것의 사용 방식을 결정합니까?
We reached out to Peter Thiel as well
우리는 피터 틸과
as Palantir because we had a lot of
팔란티어에 연락해 많은
questions.
질문을 던졌습니다.
Unfortunately, none of them were answered.
하지만 안타깝게도 그 어떤 질문도 답을 받지 못했습니다.
In 2012, Peter Thiel said,
2012년, 피터 틸은 이렇게 말했습니다.
One of the things I like about technology
제가 기술에서 좋아하는 점 중 하나는
is that when technology is unregulated, you can
기술이 규제되지 않을 때에는
change the world without getting approval from other
다른 사람들의 승인을 받지 않고도 세상을 바꿀 수 있다는 것입니다.
people.
그것이 제가 좋아하는 점입니다.
At its best, it's not subject to democratic
최상의 경우, 그것은 민주적
control and not subject to the majority, which
통제나 다수의 뜻에 종속되지 않는데,
I think is often hostile to change.
저는 다수가 종종 변화에 적대적이라고 생각합니다.
A recent venture Thiel backed is called Erebor,
최근 틸이 지원한 벤처 중 하나는 에레보르라는 이름으로,
a crypto bank named after the mountain in
『호빗』에서 살인적인 용이 보물을 쌓아두는 산의
The Hobbit where a murderous dragon hordes treasure.
이름을 딴 암호화폐 은행입니다.
And now Trump is pushing one of Thiel's
그리고 이제 트럼프는 틸의
wilder ideas, low-tax freedom cities where corporations
더 과격한 아이디어 중 하나인 '저세율 자유 도시'를 밀고 있는데,
can operate without federal regulations.
기업이 연방 규제 없이 운영할 수 있는 곳입니다.
We'll actually build new cities in our country
우리는 우리나라에
again.
새로운 도시들을 다시 실제로 건설할 것입니다.
These freedom cities will reopen the frontier, reignite
이 자유 도시는 개척지를 다시 열고
American imagination.
미국인의 상상력을 다시 불붙일 것입니다.
Freedom cities aren't just for making a lot
자유 도시는 단지 돈을 많이 벌기 위한
of money.
것만이 아닙니다.
The goal is also to conduct research without
목표는 정부의 승인 없이
governmental approval.
연구를 수행하는 것이기도 합니다.
One such place already exists, Prospera in Honduras.
그런 곳은 이미 존재합니다, 온두라스의 프로스페라입니다.
You already know who helped fund it.
그것의 자금 지원에 누가 도움을 줬는지, 여러분은 이미 알고 있습니다.
The libertarian utopia Peter Thiel dreams of no
피터 틸이 꿈꾸는 자유지상주의 유토피아는 더 이상
longer needs Mars or the open ocean.
화성이나 넓은 바다를 필요로 하지 않습니다.
It's being built right in America.
그것은 바로 미국 안에서 만들어지고 있습니다.